A Finding Aid to the Kenneth Snelson Papers, 1947-2016, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Project Files, 1947-2016; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 10.8 Linear feet Boxes 6-17
  - Sculptures, 1948-2016; 3.1; Archival Resource Key; 7.9 Linear feet Boxes 6-14
    - Mozart (1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Photographic Material, 1982; 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
      - Photographic Material, Purchase, NY, 1985; 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
      - Printed Material, 1982-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - New Dimensions (1977), 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - New Dimensions, Soft Landing (1977), 1977-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
    - Newport (1968), 1968-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Northwood (1969), 1969-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Northwood II (1969-1970), 1969-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    - Omega (1972, 1993), 1972-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Osaka (1969-1973), 1969-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Paper Column (1998), Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Planar Pieces (1960-1963), 1959-1963; 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Plastic Tube Pieces (1974), Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Post Pieces (2006-2008), 2006-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Pyramid Piece (1993), 1993-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Rador (1975), 1975-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Revolver (1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Sag Harbor I, 1965; 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Sag Harbor II (1965), 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Sag Main Street (1965-1966), 1965-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Shoebox Sculpture (1993), 1993-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Sigma Data (1975), 1975-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Six #1 (1966), 1966-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Six #2 (1968), 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Six by Eight (1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Six Strut String (2002), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Six Strut Studies (1996), 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Sixty and One Half Degrees (1992), circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Sleeping Dragon (2002), 2002-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Skywalker (1999), 1999-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8-9)
    - Small Sculptures, 1970s-2010s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
    - Sprawl Piece (1974), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Spring Street (1964), 1962-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Stage Five (1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Sun River (1967), 1967-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Star Works, Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
      - Double Star (1959), 1959-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Star (1979), 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Super Star (1966), 1961-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - Tall Star (1979), 1979-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Tall Tail (1976), Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
      - Hamburg, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - San Diego, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - Photographic Material, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Technical Drawings and Notes, General, 1960s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Tetrakai (1979), 1979-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Three Way Modules (1972), 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Triple Crown (1989, 1991), Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, 1989-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Invoices, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Materials (Tubes, Cables, and Hubs), 1980-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Photographic Material, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
      - Printed Material, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Twist (1993), 1993-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - T-Zone Flight (1995), Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, 1993-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Invoices, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Photographic Material, 1993-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Printed Material, 1993-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Vine Street (1966), 1966-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Vortex, V-X (1966), 1966-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15-16)
    - Wedding Sculpture (1996), Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Welded Sculptures (1993), Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Wiggin's Fork (1968), 1968-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Wing I (1992), 1992-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 20-21)
    - Wing II (1997), 1997-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Woodfield Mall Sculpture (1971), 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Wood Sculptures in Sagaponack (1964-1965), 1964-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Wooden 'X' Sculptures (1948-1997), 1948-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "World Fair," Electronica (1964), 1964-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Woven Stick Pieces (1965), 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - X Module (1979), 1979-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - X Piece (1967), 1967-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - X Tetra (1969-1970), 1969-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - List of Sculptures, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Towers and Columns, 1960-2016; 3.2; Archival Resource Key; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 14-15
    - Barrel Tower (2001), Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Core Towers (1974), 1974-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Core Towers (1962, 2002-2003), 1962-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Expanding and Contracting Tower (1981), 1981-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 14-15)
    - Expanding and Contracting Tower (2001), Penn Station, 1974-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Equilateral Quivering Tower (1973-1993), 1973-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 17-18)
    - Needle Tower (1968), 1968-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
    - Needle Tower (1968), 1968-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Needle Tower II (1969), Kröller-Müller, 1969-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
    - Spring Street Towers, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Tapered Towers (1965-1968), 1965-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Trigonal Tower (1963), 1962-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Tower of Light (1963), 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Virlane Tower (1980), 1978-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - X Planar Tower (1960), 1960-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - X Tower (1973), 1973-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Zig Zag Tower (1997), 1997-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Atom Model, 1960-2014; 3.3; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 15-16
    - Correspondence with Scientists, 1963-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Letters from Snelson, 1962-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, Letters to Snelson, 1963-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Notes, Development of "Portrait of an Atom", 1962-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Photographic Material, 1979-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Printed Material, 1964-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Research, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Research, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Writings, Archival Resource Key (Box 16)
      - "Portrait of an Atom", 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - "Magnetic Analogy", 1979-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - "Circles, Spheres, and Atoms", 2002-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Various Articles, 1963-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Writings by Others, 1979-1012; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Computer Pictures, 1987-1996; 3.4; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 16
    - Silicon Graphics 3130 Computer, 1987-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
    - Wavefront Software, 1987-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Artworks, A-C, 1987-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Artworks, D-M, 1987-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Artworks, N-W, 1987-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Patents, 1947-2004; 3.5; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 16
    - 3-D Weaving, 2002-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Atom Model, 1964-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Film Splicer, 1947-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Magnet, Toy, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Planar Sculptures, 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Tensegrity, United States, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Tensegrity, Japan and Canada, 1962-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Cataloging and Publishing, 1986-2015; 3.6; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 16-17
    - Aperture Foundation, 1987-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Chronology, 1927-1975, 2002-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Hudson Hills Press, 2003-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Inventory of Works, circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Inventory of Works, circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - "Not in My Lifetime," Manuscript, 1985-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - "Weaving: Mother of Tensegrity," Text, circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Exhibition and Gallery Files, 1963-2016; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2.9 Linear feet Boxes 17-20
  Exhibition and gallery files date from 1963-2016 and document dozens of exhibitions and galleries that have represented Snelson over the years in the Unites States, Europe, and Japan. Items include correspondence, photographic material of artworks, installations, and openings, exhibitions lists, floorplans, shipping receipts, invoices, contracts, and printed material including exhibitions catalogs, announcements, and clippings.
  The series is arranged as two subseries.
  4.1: Exhibitions, 1963-2008
  4.2: Galleries, 1966-2016
  - Exhibitions, 1963-2008; 4.1; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 17-18
    - Snelson Structures (1963), Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Five Sculptures (1968), 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Fort Worth Art Center Museum (1969), Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Stress Structures (1969), Rijksmuseum Kröller Müller, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Kunsthalle Düsseldorf (1970), 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Hannover Kunstverein (1971), Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Waterside Plaza (1974), 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Hakone Open-Air Museum, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Nationalgalerie Berlin, 1974-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 12-13)
    - Wilhelm-Lehmbruck Museum (1977), 1972-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Structures (1980), Birmingham Museum of Art, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Retrospective (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 17)
      - General, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 16-17)
      - Hirshhorn Museum Photographs, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Albright-Knox Art Gallery Photographs, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Portrait of an Atom (1981), Maryland Academy of Sciences, 1978-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 20-21)
    - Portrait of an Atom (1982), Traveling Exhibition, 1964-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Portrait of an Atom, Exhibition Catalog Responses, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - Panoramic Photographs (1984), DeCordova Museum, 1984-1985; 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - SIGGRAPH Traveling Exhibition, 1988-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - International Sculpture Center (1989), 1989-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - The Nature of Structures (1989), 1987-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Musée de Grenoble (1997), 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Digital Stone Exhibition (2008), Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Group Exhibitions, 1967-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 10-11)
  - Galleries, 1966-2016; 4.2; Archival Resource Key; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 18-20
    - Anderson Gallery, 1991-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - ConStruct Gallery, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Contemporary Sculpture Center, Tokyo, 1991-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 14-17)
    - Contemporary Sculpture Center, Daibiru Building Project, 1998-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - Dwan Gallery, 1966-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Estelle Dodge Associates, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Galeria Carl van der Voort, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Galerie Hoffmann, 1997-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - John Weber Gallery, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Laurence Miller Gallery, 1994-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Marlborough Gallery, 1997-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 9-10)
    - Maxwell Davidson Gallery, 1994-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Sonnabend Gallery, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Yoh Art Gallery, 1989-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 13-16)
    - Zabriskie Gallery, 1978-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Zabriskie Gallery, 1978-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Gallery Files, General, 1975-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Photographic Material, 1951-2004; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 20-22
  Photographic material dates from 1951-2004 and includes photographic prints, slides, negatives, contact sheets, and transparencies, as well as notes that Snelson kept about camera types and photographic processes. Primary subjects include artwork, New York City, studio spaces, and travel destinations. Although personal photographs are included here, a bulk of the material pertains to Snelson's fine art photography in which he experiments with panoramic photography and stereoscopic photography. Snelson organized many photographs by the type of camera he used, which can be found under the "Camera Type" heading.
  - Artwork, 1959-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Camera Journal, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Camera Type, Archival Resource Key (Box 20)
    - 16 Inch Circuit Camera, 1977-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Hulcher (Panoramas), 1974-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Hulcher (Studio Shots), 1970-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Inventory, 1981-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Kodak Panorama, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Stereo, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 11-12)
    - Stereo, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Widelux (Panoramas), 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Circle Panoramas, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Clouds, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - New York, Various Locations, 1979-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - New York City, Sullivan Street, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - New York City, West Side Highway, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Scale Figures, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Snelson with Cameras, 1981-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Studios, Archival Resource Key (Box 21)
    - 35 West 26th Street, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - 140 Sullivan Street, 1972-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Berlin, 1959-1960; 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    - George Rickey's Studio, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Sagaponack, New York, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Spring Street, 1960-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - York Avenue, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Travel, Archival Resource Key (Box 21)
    - Bombay, India, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Greece, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Italy and Greece, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Italy, 1982; 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 12-14)
    - Venice, Italy, 1982; 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 15-16)
    - Japan, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Kyoto, Japan, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Paris, 1980-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 19-20)
    - Paris, Bois de Boulogne, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1960-2015; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 22-23
  Printed material dates from 1960-2015 and is predominantly comprised of exhibition catalogs, although a few articles and clippings are filed here as well. The series also includes two issues of the International Journal of Space Structures and a collage portrait of Snelson by Sam Wiener.
  - Articles and Clippings, 1964; 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Collage of Snelson by Sam Wiener, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 3-5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1980s-2010s; Archival Resource Key (Box 23, Folder 1-5)
  - International Journal of Space Structures, 1996; 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 23, Folder 6)